<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>At the Starre-Chamber the twentieth of Iune, 1634. Present: Lord Archbishop of Canterbury. ... Master Secretary VVindebank.</title>
            <title>Miscellaneous Documents. 1634-06-20</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B13079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9017</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide 506.h.12[39]</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99892615</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99892615</idno>
            <idno type="VID">185766</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B13079)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185766)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; C2:3[39])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>At the Starre-Chamber the twentieth of Iune, 1634. Present: Lord Archbishop of Canterbury. ... Master Secretary VVindebank.</title>
                  <title>Miscellaneous Documents. 1634-06-20</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Privy Council.</author>
                  <author>Charles I, King of England, 1600-1649.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Court of Star Chamber.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 sheets ([2] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Robert Barker, printer to the Kings most excellent Maiestie: and by the assignes of Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXXIIII. [1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Text begins: This day the board did take into consideration the complaints made from seuerall parts of the kingdome, ...</note>
                  <note>Limiting the use of farthing tokens, with extract of Star Chamber decree of 25 Apr. 1634 forbidding their payment as wages, etc.---STC.</note>
                  <note>Arms 24; Steele notation: complaints  Starre-  2) as and.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:185766:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head type="royal_insignia">
               <figure>
                  <q xml:lang="frm">HONI ❀ SOIT ❀ QVI ❀ MAL ❀ Y ❀ PENSE</q>
                  <q xml:lang="frm">DIEV · ET · MON · DROIT</q>
                  <figDesc>royal blazon surmounted by a crown and flanked by the English lion on one side and the Scottish unicorn on the other</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> At the Starre-Chamber <date>the twentieth of Iune, 1634.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Preſent:
<list>
                  <item>Lord Archbiſhop of Canterbury.</item>
                  <item>Lord Keeper.</item>
                  <item>Lord Archbiſhop of Yorke.</item>
                  <item>Lord Priuie Seale.</item>
                  <item>Lord high Chamberlaine.</item>
                  <item>Lord Chamberlaine.</item>
                  <item>Earle of Bridgewater.</item>
                  <item>Lord Cottington.</item>
                  <item>Lord Newburgh.</item>
                  <item>Maſter Treaſurer.</item>
                  <item>Maſter Comptroler.</item>
                  <item>Maſter Secretary Coke.</item>
                  <item>Maſter Secretary Windebank.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His day the Board did take into conſideration the complaints</hi> made from ſeuerall parts of the Kingdome, concerning the ſtopp and refuſall of Farthing Tokens, proceeding aſwell from the abuſe in counterfeiting the ſame, as in cauſing the ſame to paſſe, aſwell in payments, as for commodities and for wages to Workemen and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, in greater quantities then was intended.</p>
            <p>And whereas vpon a Decree lately made in the High Court of Starre-Chamber, the fiue and twentieth day of April laſt, wherein Sir <hi>Francis Crane</hi> Knight, was Plaintife againſt <hi>William Hawkes</hi> and others for making and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of counterfeit Farthing Tokens: Their Lordſhips did call to minde, that there was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration likewiſe had, and prouiſion made by the ſaid Decree againſt the abuſe in forcing the ſame vpon men for Wages and in other paiments, and directing the right vſe to be made of them for the good and benefit of the Subiect, according to His Maieſties Royall Intention, and the Proclamations publiſhed in that behalfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:185766:2"/>
            <p>It was therefore by the Board thought fit and ordered, that ſo much of the ſaid Decree as concerned the regulating of the buſineſſe <hi>de futuro,</hi> ſhould be ſet downe in this order, and together with the ſame be forthwith printed and publiſhed, which part of the ſaid Decree doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly follow in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THe Court being informed, that by the abuſe of ſome particular perſons, whoſe only ayme is, to make a priuate gaine and profit to themſelues, His Maieſties people are much abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in many parts of this Kingdome; and poore Labourers, whoſe neceſſities are ſuch as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forceth them to take their Hire in any Money, are compelled many times to take their whole weekes wages in Farthings, from ſuch as buy great quantities at low rates, and make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity thereby: Which abuſe, as it is already become a great burden and grieuance to His Maieſties people in many parts of this Realme, ſo it is to be feared, it will hereafter turne to the great diſaduantage of His Maieſties Patentees, if it be not remedied by a timely reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Their Lordſhips being therefore willing to preuent and meet with ſuch growing euills, and deſirous to remoue the Inconueniences of forcing His Maieſties Subiects to take ſuch great quantities of Farthings in payments: Which Farthing Tokens rightly vſed, are of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues very vſefull and neceſſary, and were made chiefly for the reliefe of the poore, and to bee vented and vſed onely for exchange in ſmall ſummes, but not to be put vpon any in great pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; Haue thought fit and ordered, and it is by this their Lordſhips Sentence declared, that it is vtterly vnlawfull, and expreſſely contrary to the true meaning of His Maieſties Letters Patents and Proclamation, that any ſuch Farthing Tokens ſhould be inforced vpon any poore Labourers, or Workemen, or other perſons in any payments either of great or leſſer ſummes.</p>
            <p>And they declare further, That they thinke it fit that no perſon ſhould pay aboue two pence in Farthings to any other perſon at any time. And this Court doth alſo declare it to be vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any man to buy or barter for any Farthings, at or for any leſſer rate then they are vſually vented by His Maieſties Patentees, to whom the ſole making thereof is granted, and vpon whom the rechange thereof lyeth at the ſame rate; And if any perſon ſhall be found herein to offend in either of theſe kinds, This Court is reſolued ſeuerely to puniſh the Offenders. And the Court doth withall hold fit, and deſire that His Maieſtie ſhould be moued to declare and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the ſame, by his Highneſſe Proclamation to be publiſhed through this Kingdome, that ſo the true vſe of theſe Farthing Tokens intended for the good of the poore may be continued, and the abuſes aforeſaid may either be preuented or puniſhed.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the King.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Imprinted at London by Robert Barker, Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Maieſtie: and by the Aſsignes of Iohn Bill. M.DC.XXXIIII.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
